<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Pheng Heong&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Pheng Heong&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 12:10:34 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A morning at SMART</title>
      <link>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-05-09-a-morning-at-smart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 12:10:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-05-09-a-morning-at-smart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Singapore-MIT Alliance for Research and Technology (SMART) is a research enterprise. I got an opportunity to attach myself to the team that is working on SimMobility, a simulation platform. SimMobility is part of the Future Urban Mobility interdisciplinary research group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/FiE44QfmAFw/maxresdefault.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A screenshot of the SimMobility simulation&#34; title=&#34;What my work might look like&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived in the morning about 9.40 AM. In a possible fore-shadow of the kind of working hours over here, the person at Security informed me about an access card that handled the doors which were locked after 6 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I did not have an access card, a person unlocked the door for me when I rang the bell at the entrance to the SMART office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My project manager had not arrived yet, so I spent several minutes at the reception area. On the coffee table, there were several copies of The Straits Times in a small pile. The Straits Times is a newspaper which has an online reputation of being state-controlled. There was also a magazine which lay un-opened in its plastic wrapping. The stylised font obfuscated its title. &amp;lsquo;Sian times&amp;rsquo;, it seemed to say to my struggling comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person working as a &amp;lsquo;senior software engineer&amp;rsquo; walked in. I had met him before, during my interview. He made eye contact with me, and, without breaking his stride, he went into the office. Wordlessly leaving me at the reception area, he had intimated what his responsilibities were (or were not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two people were seated a table in the office, facing me. One was consulting the other. &amp;lsquo;We are willing to teach, but you must be willing to learn,&amp;rsquo; my project manager had said during my interview. Looking at these two, I wondered whether it was a positive demonstration of behaviour within the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My project manager walked into the office as I surfed the Internet using the Wifi network. &amp;ldquo;Lesson #2: Learn to mind your business,&amp;rdquo; a heading said on the web-page on my laptop screen, which was navigated to a blog post about personal financial security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She showed me to a spot at a table, and mentioned the access card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the table, the two people I had seen previously were still on their laptops. The one who had asked the other did so again. I wondered if, like me, she was an undergraduate who was here on a Final-year project. I wanted to feel less alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll introduce you to the team later,&amp;rdquo; my project manager had assured. I said hi to the two people across the table, and made eye contact. As I did so I thought about the bows that South Koreans did when they met people. I imagined the respect that that would have conveyed. I wondered if that could help with the awkwardness of meeting people for the first time. Convention had its purpose. I was certainly feeling the awkwardness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started up the Linux virtual machine on my Windows operating system, and tried to occupy myself with my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the two, one had fair skin, the other being dark of colour. Both appeared Asian. As a vegetarian, I wondered about their diet, and tried to guess their nationality and ethnicity. The one on my left might be Chinese. The one in front of me might be Indian. These were guesses that would not matter very much if the conversation in future was going to be anything like this morning&amp;rsquo;s: reserved and purposeful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space seemed hushed, cold, and dull. The word &amp;lsquo;exciting&amp;rsquo; did not seem to fit with how the place looked. With its un-read newspapers and un-used rooms, the word &amp;lsquo;growing&amp;rsquo; seemed to suit the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writings on the floor-to-ceiling glass partitions injected some much-needed personality into the place. &amp;ldquo;Call me 4 lunch&amp;rdquo; said a scribble on a cubicle partition. &amp;lsquo;Non-beards,&amp;rsquo; pointed an arrow to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Do you wear a hat indoors?&amp;rsquo; asked the senior sofware enginner from earlier. He was smiling. It was a newsboy cap. I thought it could become my trademark. &amp;ldquo;The cap&amp;rdquo;. Pushing worries about being a limit to the productivity of the team aside, I thought I could live with that nickname, if I did become known by it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Half an hour with a developer</title>
      <link>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-05-07-half-an-hour-with-a-developer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 12:24:02 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-05-07-half-an-hour-with-a-developer/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday (5 May), I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/kx-singapore/events/229096747/&#34;&gt;a Meetup for the Kx community&lt;/a&gt; in Singapore. I met people who were working with software. Some of them worked at financial institutions, others at software companies. I had the opportunity to talk to a developer, whom I shall call C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C talked about his programming projects at college, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_golf&#34;&gt;code golf&lt;/a&gt;, and his experience of using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Q_%28programming_language_from_Kx_Systems%29&#34;&gt;the q language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-talked:17a00b698969c1d7fe3bd1cf94c29d07&#34;&gt;How I talked&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my conversation with C, sometimes I felt like a talk show host, in the sense that I had little to no expertise in the things that C cared about. So, to compensate for my lack of expertise, I tried a style of talking that I have seen in a video clip of a conversation between two people. The video clip is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eedgLk3b9f0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the video had seemed like a contrast of a positive example and a negative example of listening to people. I tried the positive example when I talked to C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did it work? Well, he seemed to respond enthusiastically. When I said things like &amp;lsquo;How cool is that?&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;That&amp;rsquo;s amazing!&amp;rsquo; he replied with &amp;lsquo;I know, right?&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;Exactly!&amp;rsquo; He was so excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I quickly ran into a problem. I wanted to go to the restroom, but I wanted to avoid sounding like the person in the video (who goes &amp;lsquo;Pass me the butter!&amp;rsquo;) Still, I excused myself in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;now-what:17a00b698969c1d7fe3bd1cf94c29d07&#34;&gt;Now what?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will definitely try to talk in a similar manner again when I talk to another developer, if the setting is appropriate. I had seemed to be able to keep the conversation going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, for the purpose of professionalism, I would ask questions in the style of interviews, in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The writer was at a Meetup where the food and drinks were courtesy of the people from&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.firstderivatives.com/&#34;&gt;First Derivatives&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not knowing</title>
      <link>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-05-06-not-knowing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2016 07:30:49 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-05-06-not-knowing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is almost 4 AM. I sit down at the computer and type. The words leap from my mind onto the screen. It is almost like magic. I do not feel that it is &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo; who is doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Not knowing&amp;rsquo; is what lies beyond the edge of our knowledge. At the edge, we feel discomfort. Our bodies change physically. A layer of perspiration forms on our soles and our torsos. We pace up and down repetitively. We know, without a doubt, that we have arrived at a place where unpleasant feelings await: dread, anxiety and fear. It is a place that we try to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Traveller, there is no road&amp;hellip; The footsteps are the path&amp;rdquo;. This is an expression that I remember reading a few months ago in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Not-Knowing-Turning-Uncertainty-Possibility/dp/1907794484&#34;&gt;a book on the subject of &amp;lsquo;Not knowing&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The words of the authors come to my mind now. They write that it is difficult to balance the act of informing the reader, with the subject matter itself. The book may make the authors seem like experts on &amp;lsquo;Not knowing&amp;rsquo;, but they emphasise that they are no more adept than we are at navigating the unknown. As if to hammer home the point that they are not experts, the authors have sought wisdom from various people on the endeavour of handling the unknown, in a particularly illuminating section, which is about following the wisdom of people with relevant experience, and essentially staying humble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has driven me to such a dark place, and into such an uncomfortable position? I am encountering the unknown as I produce this post. Never in my life have I embarked on such a pursuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would I be able to make the post funny? Who should I write the post for? How good am I as a comedian with a blog? Worry after worry has flooded my mind before I can even sit down to write. Writing a blog post had become a matter of demonstrating my competence and a potential source of embarrassment. I feel the way that I have felt in my final year of high school as I prepared for my examinations and &amp;lsquo;O&amp;rsquo; Levels: a mixture of nervousness and uneasiness. I gulp down two litres of water. About ten years ago, while preparing for examinations, I did almost the same thing. My mother exclaimed then: &amp;lsquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know why you are drinking so much water! Is it to relieve your stress?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t feign expertise,&amp;rsquo; the book seems to warn from my memories, &amp;lsquo;as tempting as it may be&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea that what I have read in the &amp;lsquo;Not knowing&amp;rsquo; book would come to my mind as I begin my confrontation with the unknown, which at this moment is how to produce a public blog post. While I have blogged in the past, it was done anonymously. I am uncertain about writing this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I notice how shallow my breaths are. I let out an exhalation and count a few breaths. I have not even been aware that dealing with the unknown would constrict my breath in such a manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In writing this blog post, I have drawn on the investigative strength and effort of people who write books, such as Steven D&amp;rsquo;Souza and Diana Renner, who co-wrote &amp;lsquo;Not knowing&amp;rsquo;. They are like a tug on your hand in pitch darkness. These are tugs that prompt a way forward when there is no light. &amp;lsquo;Close your eyes to see,&amp;rsquo; the authors write. I had not understood it when I was reading the book. I had thought I had, but I had not. Now, while writing this post, I am reminded of one afternoon at a place in Singapore called Dialogue in the Dark. I had been blindfolded and led by my hand through passageways and obstacles. I was unaccustomed to the loss of my sight, and relied on my other senses and the easy banter with the person who was pulling me by the hand, and guiding me. Near the end of the activity, it was revealed that my guide was blind. I was touched by this revelation and reversal of societal roles. I teared up. In the process of writing this post, the &amp;lsquo;Not knowing&amp;rsquo; book had felt like the hand of the blind guide. Just as she had provided direction and company to me while I fumbled and moved in the un-seeable corridors of Dialogue in the Dark, the book guides me as I write this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realise that the stories of those who have gone before us can help us in unexpected ways. Maybe this is why storytelling is such a rich and universal tradition. Maybe this is why reading should be encouraged among people of all ages. But in the spirit of not knowing, I may be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I gain some measure of expertise while writing this post, I realise that the value of my experience is in helping others in their own experiences of the unknown. Call me naive, but I would rather have somebody else go on their own journey into the unknown, than have people follow my words carelessly. I realise that a so-called expert cannot help me realise what I have to realise on my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe, this is the value behind the book&amp;rsquo;s section on &amp;ldquo;Beginner&amp;rsquo;s mind&amp;rdquo;. If only I can confront the unknown as beginners do! If only the company of beginners can make me a beginner myself! What wouldn&amp;rsquo;t I give to have the opportunity to be a beginner again, and embark on the journey into the unknown once more. In a way, I&amp;rsquo;m envious of beginners. Those who haven&amp;rsquo;t walked the path have the opportunity to develop uniquely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, my greatest value to people is in guiding them to go on their own journeys into the unknown, so that they can develop and grow in their own unique ways. Perhaps this is the answer to the question of &amp;lsquo;What is the meaning of life?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, then again, I&amp;rsquo;m no expert. I&amp;rsquo;m a beginner at blogging and writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are others who are wiser than myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They may not wish to be known as experts, but when it comes to guiding people on their own journeys of &amp;lsquo;Not knowing&amp;rsquo;, Steve D&amp;rsquo;Souza and Diana Renner did well. This is my experience after reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why am I blogging?</title>
      <link>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-04-26-why-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 06:49:28 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://phtan.github.io/blog/post/2016-04-26-why-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As this is the first post, I thought that I would take some time to lay out my motivations for starting a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lawyer argued for it (well, kinda)&lt;br /&gt;
Mike Cernovich runs several websites, and in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dangerandplay.com/2014/11/25/name/&#34;&gt;a post on one of them&lt;/a&gt;, he advises the reader to claim ownership over his/her name in cyberspace. This allows me to have some measure of control over what gets shown about me on Google search result pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because I can, and I have&lt;br /&gt;
Rick Warren &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/rick_warren_on_a_life_of_purpose?language=en&#34;&gt;gave a TED talk&lt;/a&gt; in which he said that a person has three things in his hand: Income, influence, and identity. What&amp;rsquo;s in my hand? It&amp;rsquo;s a laptop. I can become a blogger. I can influence people with what I write, as unimaginable as it sounds right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to practise writing&lt;br /&gt;
One of my dreams from childhood is to write. I wanted to write to entertain. I wanted to craft expressions. I wanted to keep myself company, and in a weird way, I had accomplished that through writing. When I was a child I used to spend time at my grandparents&amp;rsquo; place, and once, my uncle gave me a piece of paper and a pencil to occupy me. &amp;lsquo;Write a story,&amp;rsquo; he said. So I did. I wrote a story about life on another planet, as far as I can recall. And I was a little perplexed that he had no comments nor reaction after reading it. Now, adult me seems to be struggling with grammar and smoothness of expression. Hopefully, blogging would get me into a habit of writing and ameliorate the afore-mentioned problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for the first post. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>